[Music]
hello and welcome to the junkyard love
podcast
at what age do we learn how to have
better conversations
at what age do we learn to have better
conversations with ourselves
[Music]
it is shocking to almost none who
participate in the western culture that
the last few years have been filled with
division
confusion and disagreement across the
board our society seems to be riddled
with fear
blame finger-pointing and bad othering
this experiment of unity for the human
civilization is bearing its teeth and
backing into corners of walls that
threaten to crumble when pushed against
as a participant in america myself i am
greatly confused
it seems we are meeting each other at
our differences and neglecting the root
of why we would ever strive to mend
those differences
the fear-based systems of the human
organism are constantly deployed against
the enemy we see in our neighbor
the miraculous skill of language
actively splits and becomes less precise
as conversations progress
farther from progress and closer to
interior based outward projections of
our own
traumas many of us have become wounded
animal versions of ourselves
but lack the wisdom to notice it it is
not new to note that when we hold up a
mirror to ourselves
we see our flaws before our own beauty
we see our instant judgment in
comparison to
others much more quickly than we see an
aging and changing organism of biology
thus the beauty of reality is denied
what we think we are stands abruptly in
front of the truth of our reflections
has the ego evolved to be so foolish
that it protects us from personal pain
at every cost but the future of our
togetherness as a planet
the ever-growing swiftness of
technological advancement whisks us off
of our feet and into a less humanizing
version of conversation
the progress of the meme that condenses
elaborate thought and complex meaning
down to bite-size entertainment
has gripped tightly to moore's law and
threatens to shortcut us right out of
the understanding we assume we know so
well
as technology improves in a certain
direction the future of humans go with
it
the fast intertwining of the computer
data and human mind
leaves much of the human behind our
obsession with facts as a representation
of absolute truth
tramples the complexity of the human
imagination and ability to love and seek
beauty
as we try to condense shortcut and
simplify the human experience
we bulldoze the ability to police our
own limbic and nervous systems
we grow farther from the skills of
observing thought in identifying with an
overarching goal that stands outside of
our group identity
the great hack that is underway in the
zeitgeist of modern culture is precisely
on task to simplify the human art form
into yeses and no's
ones and zeros us and them
social media has changed the culture and
direction we are going as culture
the addictions to technology as a way of
communicating and thinking
blinds us from our own validity and
group reassurance thinking
the shortcutting of dopamine hits has
begun to wire each of our brains to skip
over self-reflection and sitting with
ourselves
the pain of boredom seems harder to bear
than the truth that we now all play a
role in the future of mankind
as we fight over the king's throne and
dig up mistakes of the past to tear each
other down
the existential threat grows nearer
it is my belief that modern western
culture possesses a mind virus
a mayan virus that uses our fear-based
bodily responses and untrained egoic
reactions
to keep us immensely unaware of our own
hand in the downfall of our futures
this way of thinking blinds us from
seeing that it is parasitic and it
spreads across our oceans to infect the
minds of anyone with a phone in hand
a crisis of meaning is swiftly underway
in the human psyche and the direction we
march onwards to
simply hopes to step over ever having to
think about it
we consume more data than ever and very
few of us fully comprehend
how to make sense of any of it actually
i feel that none of us possess the power
alone to compute the data we assume we
know so well
the time of human history to come
together and attempt to understand what
this data means strikes now
we are looking at each other all wrong
facts
fiction neither matters when there is
none to argue it
dear humanity we have changed the
internet has quickened the building of
something strange
and it is our duty as soul in a meet
vehicle
to attempt to understand what we are and
where we should be going
the average man and woman can no longer
afford to pollute the information
oncology with the feedings that make
themselves feel better at the cost of
togetherness
we are each of the planet earth and none
is promised
we must get better we must not buckle
down
on our group identities and tribalistic
comforts but rather we must practice
awareness awareness of what we are and
what it means to search for meaning
the small mouth movements of the
ape-like human form words that attempt
to describe
and decrypt something much deeper that
we all have access to
the truth of the human heart and
consciousness cannot be expressed with
words alone
in physical reality we have to learn to
look past the world and deeper into the
essence of meaning and communication
we waste time by creating the reality tv
show versions of problem solving
we must respect the gift of language by
searching for deeper meaning
within each word we must choose to
sharpen the ability
to possess more than one perception in
mind when deciphering the words of
another of our brothers and sisters
the union we choose to participate in
takes work
pride courage and ability to change
growth of the planet is at the hands of
the human pilot and ignorance can be
unwound with knowledge and change
to break the fever our society possesses
we must each look inward and return to a
child like mind
why is it that we do the things we do
how is it that our
individual truth is more true than that
of our neighbor
how have we arrived at this truth and
the truth before that
there is really nobody steering the ship
our actions conversations and beliefs
have consequences
the consequences control our perception
of reality and we bring that reality to
each interaction with one another
our leaders are infected with the same
mind virus that threatens us
average persons we must work together
and meet where we truly are to solve the
problem of problem solving itself
we have to change the way we have been
doing things in that process
however messy requires more cooks in the
kitchen
the next conversation you have ask
yourself if you are holding
both yours and the other person's
perceptions in mind
are you waiting for your turn to speak
are you itching to respond with an
argument rebuttal that will squash their
truth
are you actively listening and
questioning your knowledge in order to
fully allow
theirs in are you afraid of change are
you fearful of being wrong
does your conversation style elicit
emotional regulation
is your facial expression contorted is
your body language tensed up while the
other person speaks
do you help them to express their true
meaning or do you attempt to stump them
so you can win a small victory of words
great problems require different types
of conversations and deep understanding
of one another's upbringing
backgrounds language fears desires and
end goals
it is time to upgrade and expand our
conversation skills as well as the
awareness
of our own human systems amidst our own
conversations
let us not allow things like texting and
social media
to push us to forget that words are
simply the tools a human uses to express
something
much deeper as our brilliant minds
decipher
at infinite lengths and speeds let us
not forget the purpose that love can
serve with each interaction
ask yourself if the mind virus of
information is causing your sense-making
apparatus
to break down in real time by turning
every word exchange into debate
argument and bad other in this series of
episodes spencer and i will attempt to
make sense of what is going on here to
cause such great division
and confusion amongst neighbors and
fellow humans
we will stumble and ramble our way to
formulating the questions that need
asked and the answers that present
themselves
we will try to police our own bias and
emotional states
our own judgments our own assessments
and our own blind spots
as new problems emerge for the human
condition we must present and practice
new ways of conversation and problem
solving neither of us claim to be fully
right
to be the most educated to know the most
truths
nor to have the correct psychosemantic
tools but we embark on this multiple
part series because it is difficult
important and we just don't see many
trying to meet the confusions from this
lens of perception
rather than claim the ability to educate
the listeners
we hope to usher an individual epiphany
by way of exploring and widening our own
thoughts
these conversations will undoubtedly be
messy at first
but as we determine the correct
definitions and jump from stepping stone
to stepping stone
we hope the path shows itself and the
journey creates
sparks of wisdom for different types of
listeners at different points of their
lives along the way
we have no grandiose ideas of being
special omniscient
or even particularly wise on the subject
of sense making itself
but we choose to pick up our swords and
proceed towards the battlefield
nonetheless
if individual sovereignty formulates
group coherence and strengthens our
human ability to process information and
make sense of modern life's complexities
this is the way
[Music]
mr spencer jake
so today you and i are going to embark
on
what we think will be a multiple part
series
um we've just spent the last hour
i mean they really last couple days
texting back and forth
trying to figure out how to have this
conversation
figure out how to like what are we even
trying to point at here
um the word the term sense making
it has been a huge uh uh brightness has
been kind of like the title it seems um
so i think that what we're going to try
to do here is actively
think and stumble out loud into
what we're trying to even say here which
doesn't sound really appealing to
listener
um here's what we're about to talk about
we don't know
um but i think that
overall we both see different areas of
division and incoherence
in our information ecology and in our
conversations and in the things that we
put
at the forefront of our attention
as far as importance we see
kind of our our system
theories breaking down our system um
not making any goddamn sense
um i want to
so so what we're going to try to do here
is this episode
i think will be kind of the beginning
the the
the precipice of
hopefully the other parts of this series
whether it's a five-part series or what
a few hours long each couple hours long
each whatever it needs to be
will start to formulate after this
conversation so this one
i feel like is undoubtedly going to be
messy but we're going to try to stumble
through it
keep in mind there's no rules to any of
this you know nobody wrote a book on how
to make sense and
we're living in an unprecedented time of
shift
structurally the way we communicate as
humans
our power structures are dissolving you
know like this is
with the information age and especially
what is happening right now with the
pandemic being like a non-specific
amplifier of all
things that were already problems like
we're seeing such a boiling up
of all these uh systemic and endemic
issues of communication and how we like
arrive at truth and we're gonna do our
best to sift through that but i do not
think that any
one or two men or women could ever
decisively
answer the question no doubt and and
there's also no grandiose ideas
in my head and i'm certainly sure to
agree that in your head
that we're not like the best at solving
this problem i am not a genius i am not
someone who like studies all of these
things um
my entire life i like i presented to you
before i think that i am a
creative thinker um and i'm trying to
bring that lens
to the table um not a
not a i'm right and here's why i'm right
and these people are wrong and here's
why they're wrong
not a here's my knowledge versus your
knowledge it's more of a
term i used earlier um an ushering in of
epiphany
so what i want this to do is
spark some aha moments in the listeners
of like huh
that is i didn't think that way before
or
i haven't thought of that perspective or
even turn
turn turning the lens in on themselves
of
okay i i do have a perspective don't i
what is my perspective how did my
perspective form
is it helpful um i i
i so so what we'll constantly try to do
is
remember the title like i had said try
to as we kind of get going into the
weeds as we undoubtedly will
we'll try to wind it back out and be
like how is this helpful to what we're
trying to communicate here so
as we're trying to figure out what we're
communicating we will also be
checking ourselves and we'll be trying
to go meta on the conversation and we'll
try to referee
our own conversation if that makes any
sense
spencer i think we should start
and feel free to take as much time as
you need to on it and feel feel free to
expand
or ask any questions to me but you what
you were writing is
essentially what is truth yes
there's a lot of things that we just
take for granted as concepts
you know as people especially if you
haven't uh engaged in like a lot of
philosophical
um literature or uh been traditionally
trained which i have not i just
this is a hobby i'm just a guy but
the very specific definition of words
and their connotations is really
important to philosophy
and with sense making the ultimate goal
to be arrive at some kind of truth
correct so what is the actual definition
of truth and is it
can you even arrive at it like is there
an objective truth
and with our ability to perceive things
can we find it essentially
and i personally don't think that there
is an actually objective well there is
an objective reality we just can never
arrive at it because
our human lens is flawed through
uh perception our perception is the rate
limiting factor on if we can actually
view reality and since none of us are
omniscient we cannot arrive at it
actually but that should not actually
stop us from trying to
pursue it as diligently as we possibly
could
so you see it in journalism journalists
can never actually arrive at the
concrete truth because
they like all people are not omniscient
but
their whole thesis and all their code of
ethics says to arrive at the greatest
possible truth that you can
so just that i think it's a really apt
thing to note because if you haven't
thought about it it's very easy to think
yes this is true this is not i can
definitely arrive at this this is
concrete
but i would like to say that it's much
more fluid and not
up for interpretation but you need a
like a large
vast swath of data and perceptions to
arrive at some kind of ubiquitous truth
you can't just really
arrive at it innately and if you
look at the word in not such a concrete
form it really
i think opens up the question of how do
we
arrive at a proper sense making plan or
do this better because
it's going to take just a lot of brain
power to do so
and well what do you think truth is do
you think you can arrive at objectively
um i don't know because it's it's it's
instantly dissolved in
different conversations in different um
because we'd all have to have the same
perception of reality
and the same i guess upbringing in
everything to have a
common truth um i think that
truth i mean in truth is also
an evolving changing thing it's not
something that can ever be completely
arrived at it's it's uh
as our lives as we are evolution as we
are biological creatures as everything
here
is in movement in constant time um
truth changes so if we think of what
truth was
um back in roman times it's
now different than what it is now uh um
it's as we dissolve
old ways of knowing old belief systems
truth changes along with that i don't
think that truth is something that we're
trying to you know as a society discover
like it's just already here it was on
planet earth and now that humans are on
planet earth
we're gonna find the truth like it's
already it's always been there
um i think that truth definition
changes based off of what subject you're
talking about as well
yeah because empiricism actually does
technically arrive at some universal
truths like laws of physics and whatnot
or like two plus two plus four like
these are empirically true
but i feel like it gets into the weeds
and it's way more up to
perception and your ability to sense
make when it is
more social or
sociological structures that are being
questioned and the truth that is being
arrived at and yes i do believe that is
ever shifting
but i think that the loose ever shifting
truth uh makes the sense making question
and proposition way more difficult
than like uh two plus two equals four
finding a math equation or uh doing
anything empirically
because it's so open to being shaken up
and open to different perceptions
and the constant pursuit of it must be
must be had and you have to eliminate
bias and dogma to actually do that
because one of my favorite lines that
i've ever heard is uh bias and dogma
turn intelligence to impotence
so if you stop seeking out this truth
and find
facts and just hold on to them forever
you will definitely not gain anything
from that
and i think it's just a lot of the sense
making problems really come from
an inability to be flexible in such a
liquid time
of reality like this is way more liquid
than any other time we've ever had our
like borders are dissolving
transnational companies are going
everywhere
like the power of states is dissolving i
mean social media is allowing all of
this to proliferate
all information just at lightning speeds
so not being able to sift through that
is a
incredible problem that i do not
actually have
a solution for but i don't think either
of us have a solution for i think that
but i think so a lot of the problem is
a lot of us assuming that our
information is
the truth yes like we hear a lot of fake
news we hear a lot of
facts we hear a lot of um and these
things kind of bump against like
well that's true or that's untrue um
and we're arguing those we're arguing my
truth versus your truth
when neither of them are technically the
truth let's say yes
um so
so let's let's stay here with truth i
think that
if we could bring in some examples of
maybe something that we learned back in
high school like we
we're both um raised western culture
so let's say when we're learning about
the truth of something that happened in
world war ii we learned it from a book
and they're like this is true but so
um perhaps you can bring in an actual
historic example here after but
so what's written in that book i read
that book as a student 15 years old
okay this christopher columbus did this
blah blah blah okay that's true it's
true because i read in the book well
there was someone who wrote the book
right
um there they had their own perceptions
of reality they had their own
experiences they had their own
information that they read that they
heard
um if you just keep following back truth
it's like
well who told them that how did they
learn that
um i i don't mean to
unwind history but history is subjective
history is a lot of times when we're
learning about
our history it's not always the history
right
um i don't know is there anything in
that for you is it dessert uh well yeah
that's definitely a good
example of how like something that you
can hold as true is not necessarily the
truth
like an idea in general so like there is
especially when it comes to cultural
perceptions and uh historical context
because
if you talk to an american and we think
about world war ii
you think that um you know we won like
we
are the reason the deciding factor and
we did the fighting in world war
ii but in actuality if you look at any
of the data or any of the act like any
of the ubiquitous historical context
from other nations like
russia actually did most of the allied
fighting in world war ii
they had the most deaths they crossed
over the most ground i mean yes we dealt
with japan to some degree but
you don't hear that here like it's just
it is definitely highly up to perception
and that's kind of the problem because a
lot of these
things really just get uh boiled down to
narrative and bias
like from a higher level so if you have
a population
like there it's in the best interest of
whoever's writing that book to make the
country that they're living in
look really good right like the
government assigns all of this
essentially
so that can cause a massive sense-making
issue and i just think that maybe
to combat that you need more information
like i said you need
more more perspectives and then also
being curiously skeptic being a curious
skeptic
because if you just i think this is what
happens a lot
is you see people engaging in a lot of
news and if you ever go talk to anyone
or read anything about anyone who was
like did a propaganda campaign
or has tried to disseminate anything
that might be coercive
they just try to convince you more of
what you already feel
they never try to change your mind so
it's just the
ability to not necessarily follow that
and carry on trying to get more
inputs and maybe come to a
truer conclusion but never the truth so
okay so in a lot of these contexts we
have to be
agreeing on a direction in which we're
facing agreeing on
upon a direction in which which we're
going so when
in the history book example you're
trying to teach the student
knowledge so they can better navigate
the world let's say so they
so they understand why they should be
proud to be an american let's say
that's the so behind truth there's
always a
um agenda isn't the correct word oh
kinda though
i i don't want it to get mud muddied
with all truth being propaganda though
i don't want to but all perception has
bias
all perception has bias that's helpful
yeah so
so so on zooming out really quick
if we are
any information we're trying to teach
someone any truth we're trying to
communicate
there is a reason behind it there's a
this will help you in this way or this
is this is helpful for humanity in this
way this is helpful for
our group in this way this is why i'm
teaching it to you and this is why it's
truth this is why it's helpful for you
to believe it
we're trying to stack
i believe that that perception
definitely heavily relies on
the idea that whoever is disseminating
this information
is doing it in good faith and also wants
something good for you instead of having
an ulterior motive
which i think really where we run into
issues especially with
the ability to disseminate information
as fast as social media will allow us to
because now there's not like the
transmission model
of communications is not so much in
place and it's more ritualistic so
communication has
kind of become performative and all of
these perceptions
are an attempt to sway others or appear
to others in your group
to be like hey look i share those
opinions with you i'm putting them on
the internet now we can all be together
and we can come together as a group so i
don't necessarily think that that's very
altruistic but it definitely causes
a lot of division and it's really hard
to step back from that concept
because once you decide that you're in a
group and you hold all these ideals
uh what are you gonna do you just keep
performing and you
i mean like your neighbors like they've
got
the two conflicting signs politically
and they just
are bashing against each other like that
is performative
right like that's not there's nothing
signaling it's it's not a it's not a
so so why would we signal okay so i
guess we'll back up we'll say
why would we why would we be signaling
but to preface that
i gave an example to spencer my
neighbors are
there's one house that has trump signs
all over it and then the house next door
their neighbors
they have biden and harris signs all
over and then
bordering between the two there's like a
little bit of uh like a couple trees and
some grass area
um and they have
a like stop the donald it's basically
like a
hey we're on the side of biden harris
but we're also this is kind of a sign
that's like attacking the donald
the donald trump people and they kind of
they scooted that sign over
towards the side of the trump people and
to me when i see this i i don't i
certainly don't choose either side
i just wonder what's going on here i'm
just like
why is it that this is how we're
communicating why is it that
of all things that are important out of
human life
this is what we're spending our time to
this is what we're saying i'm putting a
flag in the ground this is what i
believe
and that what they believe is wrong um
but
but so a lot of what's happening here
and how we're going to lead this into
social media technology
is data's algorithm
um our groups our echo chambers these
sorts of things
are feeding us things that that
lock down our own beliefs so
for example in portland um depending on
if you're on
say the left or the right and that's the
media that you follow you don't see
things that you don't want to see
so or or the algorithms don't feed you
things that you don't want to see so
there will be
so let's say a riot in portland and
it'll say that you know it's the left
rioting and they're the bad people
whatever
and you're like what of course like who
wants that they're destroying portland
but then if you have
left side media they're showing right
down the road a couple blocks
that same night at the same time there's
like a candlelight vigil
with people singing and people coming
together so
which one is the truth we're just being
shown
two different things two different
things that are happening a block away
from each other
but one is uh feeding the narrative
of bad other and one is feeding we're
good people
and and these two people are not
watching the same exact news
so how do you make sense of that
yeah i mean well you don't honestly
which one's true right
well i would argue neither honestly
neither is the actual truth
like if you can't actually arrive with
it and i think that you
this is a slightly pivot and i apologize
but you
said you said that just the word why
and i think that that really informs
like why it's so easy to get lost in the
weeds because a lot of people don't
like why am i believing this like what
is the thesis
for me to even be fed this algorithm or
lean this way or this way like what is
my
like what is the goal of civilization
like what is the goal of my life do i
have um
like is it to spread the most human
happiness and wealth
or like you just people just stumble
upon opinions
they pick a side and then they fight
fiercely for with ever asking or
questioning
why they even got there in the first
place like what is
the deconstruction of the idea of like
why do we have systems
why do we have any of these things you
know and
it's way easier to navigate all this
climate and all this
like perceptual untruth truths half
truths if you just have
a core tenant that you can abide by that
isn't
a tribal tenant and i think it's way
easier to get sucked into all these
problems
if you just are i'm doing this
performatively to align with this side
opposed to this is the reason that i
believe these things and no matter what
side it's on which there's a false
dichotomy by the way to boil down all
political thought to left right is
absurd and no
actual political theorist would ever do
it
do i actually want am i actually
believing these things
for a reason or is it just because i've
been told to
right so okay so i guess we have to come
to uh
there's a lot there that we can pick up
on but i guess even questioning your
beliefs is a huge thing so to where you
can even get to where
this area of conversation where we're
even trying to be like what the hell's
going on here
we have to we we're people who question
our beliefs
so belief systems how are belief systems
installed in a human brain you grow up
and you know so a good example a clean
example that i think a lot of people can
agree on is
is um like kids being racist
so the when kids are being racist you
see like a video on viceland or
something and you see like a
seven-year-old like saying the n-word or
something
and it's clear that he doesn't really
know what he believes he just has been
taught it by his parents
or by the people around him growing up
um
i think there's a lot of our belief
systems that
can be unwound by just saying wait why
do i believe this who taught it to me
who taught it to them
and is it true is it helpful
as i'm going about my life is it helpful
as i'm interacting with people
that are different than me is it helpful
for me to
continue spreading this saying that it's
truth or my truth
um what do you have what do you have on
that so
belief systems i think that it's
important to
have people question their own belief
systems and i don't think many people
especially
in our let's just i'll generalize and
say our small towns some of the small
town mindsets
we don't actually question our belief
systems we don't question the
information that we're given
like the new station that you watch is
the news
right and i think that's what we're
butting up against a lot is
we're at a time where it's almost
detrimental to
the future of civilization in a sense
that sounds
incredibly intense i understand but if
we're not able to question
what we're hearing or question what
we're because because
if i'm sitting here watching um cnn fox
whatever it is
for six hours a day and then
later on i go have an argument with
my my my bullets and my
my weapons have in that argument are the
information i just learned for those six
hours
of course i'm like what are you talking
about like aren't you listening to the
same thing as me
aren't you understanding the same
arguments as me we don't realize that
that's a bias that's a
our belief systems are getting poked and
prodded um
yeah it uh it's pretty interesting
because
like all this information is being
disseminated and
you almost certainly find something that
confirms your worldview because
innately as a human you just don't like
it doesn't feel good to really be
challenged
like this thing that you've been
programmed with is just
it's your reality so anything that
more than not it becomes part of your
identity and
to actually look in and be like
well why like what is this where did
this come from why am i doing this
is this even correct especially i mean
you have the sunk cost foul so you see
in older people a lot
they'll be confronted with well
facts i'm air quoting facts or
new information that is definitely
it's more concrete than what they've
been provided
before but because they've spent their
entire life
believing this thing to then turn around
and look at the last 50 years of your
life and be like i was wrong
this thing that i tied myself was
incorrect and i
may have done some bad things said some
bad things been harmful to society
actively because i believe these
like that is your subconscious will is
it won't allow you to do it it will
reject that so the question is how do
you refrain from getting there and i
think it would be
to be innately skeptical from as young
as physically possible
because you you
you're not your political affiliate
you're not any of these ideas like these
are
concepts that are not you and in order
for you to make sense of things you
you lose well you lose the ability to
make sense of things when you start
tying yourself down and i see it myself
like i'm
a super leftist and i have to constantly
fight myself from just
knee-jerk snap agreeing with things
definitely it's very hard
actually and i'm super aware of it it's
still hard
so what identity is a good corner i
think identity is something we'll have
to spend some time on what is
identity how is it helpful to to the
human
creature the the you know where the
thing that came after apes
however that happened is up to up to
speculation i suppose but
like how is identifying with
group dynamics helpful to not only our
survival which is how it started right
like you don't want to be
like suddenly you're with 150 people and
you start disidentifying your your
you're rejected from the group
all of a sudden your life is in danger
now you don't have a promised meal
now you're kicked out of the the group
the commune that's been formed
um i identity so
let's linger on identities for a bit
okay so
the on a sociological evolutionary basis
the identity is helpful to
determine if you fit into the n-group
and then survive by assimilating in it
so if you can perceive the
characteristics of the people around you
from a
young age and be ingrained with them
you're way more likely to have a
survival chance
and deal with this homogeny better so it
i mean you can look at religion so
religion if you want to just look at it
as like a
sociological concept of order opposed to
like a belief system
it was really helpful for you not
killing your neighbors you know
if we both believe in this dude that
cares for both of us and that's what
tying us together like
i'm not going to kill your wife or i'm
not going to kill you or steal your kids
or do anything really heinous because we
live in a community
and god is watching over us so it just
creates innate order
but that is being dissolved like just
the ability to go seek outside of that
and the isolation that
modernity has allowed us to engage in
with the internet
and uh there's just a new sense of being
able to redefine yourself but i also fit
into this like extremely individualist
space and
the power structures and tribal behavior
that has lasted us up until facebook
happened
and we've been able to transmit ideas
really
quickly is just kind of crumbling in on
itself
so people not like we're having an
identity crisis as well
everyone kind of is and you're having a
couple reactions to it so you see
some people see this globalization of
the world and how everything's kind of
be
being intertwined into this like
internet
hive mind of homogeneous or a
heterogeneous
um human thought and that's like holy
this is
frightening like every power structure
that i've ever been inundated with and
every idea that i've held really true is
just being dissolved on the internet
so you react and you get scared and you
trip up even harder and
you we're really seeing that like build
a wall what is that
like i'm scared of others we gotta lock
down we need order because
the structure of society that has
prevailed for thousands of years is
completely deteriorating
right and how do you find an identity in
that
and then but also
not do that i guess is the question
well so okay so we have
i i try to always go like what what's
this step before identity like like the
one commonality that we have before
our race before our gender before blah
blah blah any of that
is we're humanity right we're we're one
humanity and we seem to be
loosening that identity like not keeping
that we
we don't have that identity uh in the
forefront of our mind or even the back
of our minds as we're having these
arguments we're arguing
here's what i believe and what um i am
owed because of my identity or what i
have been
what's been taken from me or what's been
um you know whatever it is we're
buckling down
on sides of our identity that are
unhelpful to the overall conversation
that are unhelpful to
um to actually solving the problems at
hand
we are diverting the attention of
important topics
by gripping onto our identity and
arguing there um
and and it's it's it's it's blinding us
in ways that we don't seem to understand
like we have important people on
important podiums
who should be having important
conversations and
they're not talking about anything
they're they're just arguing me versus
you
rather than us versus the problem and
so i suppose that so maybe we have to
say how does identity get in the way
of the future of humanity
well we have to start stop separating on
us versus them level
you know like borders are just lines
that we've created to justify
another you know like we so many things
and this is i don't really think it's a
fault of humanity it's just how we've
survived
you just find the in-group you find the
in-group like this is what we're
programmed to do and it's gonna take a
lot of conscious effort from really
smart people that are leading things to
make this not happen anymore
but like that somebody that i know made
a really offhanded joke about like some
kid in vietnam making his nikes and
that to me like the dehumanization of
people that don't look like you in other
places
is um neat it just must stop
because it just is causing a lot of
innate suffering and i thought that was
such like put such a microscope under it
because once you once that stops being a
person
like we are never going to be able to
co-exist and it
you see the political spectrum or
american politics
are super revolved around identity in
general because it's the easiest way to
maintain power
like it's power dynamics that are really
causing this all to happen because if
you can
convince a whole lot of people that
they're on this side
and a whole lot of other people that
they're on the other side but those
sides are actually really close
and then they kind of fight each other
this manufactures
conflict when the actual problem
is the immense coagulation of power in
these few people that essentially agree
so i just think the perception is wrong
of why
we're mad like i think that
people are upset because of their
material conditions you know life's
really hard
like our economy and uh are the the way
that america does capitalism is really
oppressive we're overworked
we don't ever have any time to actualize
and i think this is by design
and our two parties insulate themselves
so nobody else can get in no new idea is
going to get in it's like this
old bulwark of potency
and until we can kind of rally together
and realize hey man the power structures
that have been
set out in society they do not work for
any of us
and that's why we're all mad because if
you ever go listen to anyone on the left
or right
and yeah they have definite differences
and they have definitely large world
views and what they care about is like
their thesis is different if they've
arrived at one
but ultimately like everyone is
suffering
because of the system and until we can
make sense of that
come to the conclusion that your
neighbor with the other flag or whatever
is really not the problem at all
and maybe figure out what his problems
are we're not going to be able to get
through it
yeah because we're being pitted against
each other
by old men that basically believe the
same thing
and don't care about any of us and until
we can make sense of that it's going to
be a very large issue but i don't
see an end in sight because it is
they control the media they i mean the
internet
directly profits off of us division and
anger
so i watch a ted talk and fake news
spreads
five times faster and five times more
than regular news
so how do you combat that like you would
have to change the monetization scheme
of the internet that's the only way like
we would have to get money out of all
these things
or how can we as individuals as just
average
average everyday people who just work
jobs and they just
maybe they're not college educated how
do we upgrade their sense making so they
can realize like
oh okay i'm i'm my
my my limbic system my my human body is
being
hijacked here the small walnut
almond size part of my brain is being
turned on right here and pointing me at
a bad other and then stepping out wait
is that what i really think is that what
i really care about of all the things
going on in my life right now in my
personal existence if i wasn't on the
internet
my everyday monday through friday
the people i interact with what i
actually speak about with them
is this piece of information that's
being fed to me on the internet on
facebook
actually important to my life as an
individual
i believe it is not most of the time
it's like
so so how do we so let okay
remember the topic here sense making how
do we
how do we upgrade our sense making as
is is is it just in an individual
survivor so what do i keep messing up
with this word
sovereignty sovereignty yeah so i well i
think it
the problem is with that i really
believe that you are the only thing that
maybe potentially can control yourself i
mean there's a lot of convincing
research on you don't actually have
perfect agency over your life
but you do have some willpower to assert
over it and until
like you can personally upgrade your
sense-making
and gain some self-sovereignty and and
remove yourself from these
biases or maybe remove yourself
from the propensity to be dogmatic it's
going to be really hard to actually
sift through all this this cluster storm
of information that we were never
designed to intake
without coming out some kind of tribal
low-minded monster
but the problem is with that is
if you focus on the individual you never
get anything done systemically
you know because it's going to be very
hard to convince a 7.8 billion people
to become self-sovereign especially
because the material conditions for a
lot of those people
are so back-breaking they can never
actually end up being actualized
so i like how do we how do we combat
that you know like
what it's it's going to have to come
from the top down
or you're we're going to have to have a
large grassroots movement to
realize that this is a massive problem
and i really think that there's a market
for it you know you're seeing a lot of
divergent thinkers they i mean they
still kind of fall and the what i guess
what you would call a plan a
you know work within the system but they
there's a market people are tired of it
people are tired of all this and i
really think the longer this goes on
people are becoming more in tune with
how much that this is polluting all of
it and we're going to have to change
cc i do agree because i think that we
we've had this plan a plan b talk before
i think that we
we're we're being we can feel the
the the uprising right we can feel the
the unrest we we we're mad at certain
people like
you're seeing more and more of the last
i mean 2020 has been a good example of
um you know we see like the racial equal
any inequality we see
um the big powers that be like a lot of
the
the hints at uh child pedophiles we see
a lot of people like whoa that's wrong
that
we're we're mad about that we don't want
these people who are in power
to be abusing their power in the form of
like you know child slavery whatever it
is
those are intense examples but um
we're taking to the streets you know in
america at least and and even you know
in the uk
and in certain other places like there
are more and more in the last couple
years
more and more people going to the
streets they're mad about these things
they're about they're mad about blm
they're mad about
um uh which
so so unwinding it from identity
i think that how do we get to a place
where we're pointing it out the right
people
we we have anger i just don't think that
we understand our anger
is the thing i think that we're fighting
things at such a low hanging fruit level
because it's like what we understand
it's what we can conceptualize like
this is what's wrong this is this is the
person that's holding me down
but we have to keep looking higher and
higher and saying like wait what's
what's the truth of that what's the
truth of that what's the truth of that
and when we say things like systematic
what does that really mean does that
mean that the very beginning the very
start of
how we organize this union how we
organize
our our society here does that need to
be
revamped is it time for that to be
not just broken down but rethought of in
like how do we
as as humans grow in our brains become
more intelligent
as we learn new information how do we
process this information
and how do we because i'm not someone
i'm i'm very
i'm very like like peace love let's get
along
but i also understand the need for
sometimes we have to take to the streets
sometimes we do have to have
some we need to rip people out of chairs
who are refusing to give up their spot
right
so how do we aim our anger correctly
um without sense making i don't think
there's
there's an answer there i think we have
to be able to properly know who is the
enemy here
and it's not so much bad other it's not
so much
um the the enemy that my facebook has
told me
is the opposite of my beliefs it's
the system that we have here is just at
a place where it's ran its course like
let's say it's time for something
it's time for a rebirth of democracy
it's time for
new leaders which and that's a tricky
word because we never even really have
had democracy you know
like what do you mean so any
consolidation of power is technically
ant
anti-democratic correct like if we're
looking at like a radical democracy as a
definition
so you have a consolidation of power in
corporations
and the government then like this is not
actually showing the will of the people
on any real facet
correct so democracy i really like to
think about i know it's kind of a pivot
but i think it's important
it's it's it's like water you know
there's
it's there's phases of it and like
radical democracy would be steam like
you can't really control steam
it just like happens all of a sudden you
see like this big outburst but the
moment you put things
in place to now contain that or keep it
going
you ruin the essence of it so it is
something that must be
fought for forever and i as i look at
history i realize this
we kind of go from this revolution
democratize
consolidation tyranny and we're just you
see empires fall from it like
there's this dysfunction because of our
inability to step back
from the systems that have been created
and say hey
there must be a better way to organize
this the people that run these
things say that they're the best that
this is the best like
like people will say oh you know what
the american government perfect
like they democracy the democracy that
we have is
is flawless we have all these texts but
without ever looking at the root of any
of them
without ever looking at the root of
capitalism like hey is it like are any
of these systems
actually going to bring us the most
human ubiquity
and when you are fed by people in power
that these are the only way to do it
you'll never have any divergent thinking
and i think until
you can really collectively sense make
as like a group of people and remove
yourself of bias and dogma
and discern from a at least semi-similar
thesis which is definitely
hard to come to i do understand that
that these systems are one finite
they're not going to last forever and
that we need to change them i feel like
that there's a human
urge to just hold on to things that
supposedly work
and we must strip that of
how we are if we're going to change at
the rate the technology is making us
change
so do you think that we can do this
without a war or
a civilization collapse because we look
at history and
we've see it's difficult actually i
think that
something happens in a lot of our brains
is when we learn about history we read
about history
we read about the romans we read about
um just
other civilizations ending or collapsing
or their rain
coming to an end whatever it is we don't
bring it into our reality here we don't
we can't
even fathom or imagine us being in one
of those
systems like we that's how we live
that's how we form
unions that's how we interact and it's
why we
it's it's how it sets up the fact that
we go to work and we get money and
there's banking systems and all this
complex
when we learn when we read about history
it seems like we're almost disregarding
history we're doing something weird with
history i mean you see these statues
being taken down and stuff
we're trying to rewrite history which is
very weird that's like our
problem-solving when it comes to
i think that there's something happening
we intuitively or we
there's a lot of us that feel like oh
this is breaking and we look at
history we don't say
okay what did it look like right before
their stuff broke
how do we realize that we're there in
one of those
system things and not
so back to the beginning of what i just
said how do we
get to rebuilding something new without
a huge
either collapse without suffering
without war without
i mean because we're building up to the
collapse of this thing is what's
happening
yeah i will be intelligent enough to
stop that
i don't know collectively it's kind of
hard because i mean with the
ability to transmit information power
structures get upheld way easier
because all these people with all this
much all this influence all this power
are able to shove information in front
of your face
that is pro their power
essentially right so until we can
realize that the power structures
that have been put in place are what is
actually really the problem
and that um people can come to terms
with the fact that
maybe the myth of american excellency
and that we are this is the greatest way
to ever order
society may not be true and that there
always is something better it's going to
be very difficult
but it's i don't know how we're going to
get past it
so i i think of i'm not sure if this is
helpful
i think of like nationalism and
patriotism
i think um us
being there's
there's a weird difference with and i
don't know the exact definitions of
either of those two there's this weird
definition
or difference in we should be very proud
of where we're from
it should be like our that's our it's
our culture right um we should
we should care about our in in our
community
um but we shouldn't say that it's
the greatest that that's that's
unhelpful
well this is saying that it's better
than the way other people do things
is almost an irrelevant thing to say
it's not what do you compare why are you
comparing it it's
we're mixing up our pride with what we
have with it being
better than other things yeah regimes in
general
or uh governments really profit a lot
from a
blind hyper-nationalistic population
because they can justify basically
anything they do
i mean look at every war we've been in
since vietnam or since world war ii it's
been unjust
it's been in pure it's been imperialism
we're just going for
power and monetary gain and we really
because of this hypernationalism are
super blind to the atrocities that
america commits
like in the third world the global south
like we just do a lot
of damage to the global economy in
general and we cause a lot of suffering
and until we can erase those imaginary
lines and realize that these are people
too
it's really easy to look at the
government as this force for good
this american excellency myth right and
but how do you unwind that i mean the
propaganda machine is so potent
so i hate it this is just such a tough
question
it really is like how how do we really
make sense of everything while
everything
in the world is completely falling apart
not in like a
catastrophic sense but in the way that
we used to do things like sovereign
powers nations are no longer
like this bulwark of order anymore
like with this hyper communication and
the way
that the economy works in a global
fashion we're going to have to find a
situation find a way to situate
in our in the world and make sense for
ourselves that involves others outside
of our country
it's just gonna have to happen right so
how do we
hmm yeah because we we still try to
apply a political lens to even that
like uh i don't know if it's exactly the
definition but
for like globalism or um like like where
people are so
against ubi those sort of things um
i think that undeniably where we're at
as
a humanity on a planet i think that we
have just
advanced to the point where we have to
work together
as a globe in some sort of weird sense
but not just
through the lens of capitalism not just
how do we it's not just trading
agreements it's
it's i mean
we have we have global warming and we
have um
we have issues that i i think i've used
this example
in one of our conversations before we
have in
game of thrones you've watched game of
thrones yes i have so
we're fighting over thrones and we're
trying to like handle things in a
democratic view but they we have the
white walkers coming right the
white walkers being um an existential
threat
next essential threat right so how do we
realize that the way that we're handling
things is actually
ignoring the existential threat and just
we're throwing it out the window like
with step one into our conversations
when we like call each other names or we
define ourselves as red or blue or any
of those things
and the existential threat doesn't give
a if we're red or blue or left or
right
or uh we're proud to be from this
country or probably from that country
like everybody dies here
well yeah i think we're going to have to
lean into intellectualism a lot more
there's a lot of people that lean into
anti-intellectualism so like a blatant
disregard for
like empirical science which i
understand you can insert bias and dogma
into science but it's like
way more resistant than any other
structure that we've ever had
ever so when you as a power structure
have the ability to say hey global
warming is not happening and now you
create a populist that thinks that as
well
so now you get that 50 50. so now we
can't even agree on the fact that there
is an existential threat
just because communication is so quick
yeah that's a huge thing we can't agree
on the fact that there's an existence
that's a problem yeah so that's i think
that's where we really get into the
weeds of division is because
you you have agitators or
interlocutors or in interlocutor
yes somebody that engages in a dialogue
is the definition of that word but
that because that they have corporate
interests
that go against dealing with this
existential threat convince a
subset of the population that it's not
happening because that subset of the
population
is way more vulnerable to believing that
because it aligns with the worldview so
now you're having your worldview
weaponized against you
and the world is dealing with massive
existential problems i mean global
warming
global inequality uh we're having a lot
of exploitation in the global south
uh it's just there's like a lot of human
suffering that's happened and because
you've clung so tightly to your
worldview
and haven't been able to seek out any
other
perspective you now are completely
immunizing
immunized to seeing that there is an
issue and i think that that's what the
problem is
is once you come to terms with the fact
that you have a system
that is you think it's the best and you
don't want to change it
it's bad like there can always be
something better and i think that we
just get really stuck in our ways
that way and it's very easy to convince
people like a system that's technically
working for them
that they in their regular life because
your perception is not reality you know
like
the anecdote of your life does not line
up with how the world is
if you can find that person that is
susceptible to not believing these big
problems
it's really easy to weaponize it against
them until we can make enough sense of
all this
to as objectively as physically possible
look at what the what is humanity really
facing
like what are these big issues where
it's going to be very hard to deal with
them
yeah i'm trying to i'm trying to think
of where
so i feel like we so far we've sounded
we we've definitely we sound very left
which is okay um but i'm trying to how
do we
continue to appeal to just any human on
a human
level how do we explain things like
perception
how do we how do we let's even maybe
unwind even farther um
let's talk about even reality like what
what is our reality and how do our
perceptions
change what our reality is and how is
again that points to truth like how is
that
more or less truthful than the person
next to you
so i mean even going to five sense
reality like our like
what we're doing here uh j just how a
bat has his
his two ears um
the way that he sees and navigates the
world a bat's reality
is formed by echolocation he uses this
ear and this ear
bounces sound off walls and that's how
he navigates where he's going
we have our reality here by our five
senses our touch our sight
hearing our smell whatever
i think we unwinding it back that far
and then our upbringing our culture
our environment that we grow up in
our the the different systems in our
body
being feeling safe or unsafe how do all
of these things create
our perception um i know that's
incredibly unspecific i just left you
with a of
of trying to answer a question that's
not really a question but um
i'm just trying to i'm trying to
remember our overall goal here sense
making right
um how is seeing how we all have
different perceptions
helpful to our sense making and what
really is perception i guess
it's uh i mean well you use your five
senses to engage with reality
and you internally reference that to
experiences that you've had in the past
and what you deem is correct based on
what you've already believed
so and it was really
self-referential so that's why
perception is not reality because you
will usually see what you want
in life and the most information and
you'll seek out what you want
but oh i got to think about this for a
second
it's a very tough question
until you can come to terms with the
fact that your immediate perception
and reality is not actually how the
world is
in a ubiquitous total sense
very hard to combat that in general
so like because with truth not being
this complete
absolute deductive firm fact
it's very hard for society to come
together
and agree on a lot of things and i don't
really know how to remedy that
but because if we go look back at the
thesis statement for what we want at all
these structures i think it really comes
down to being able to question all of
them in general
it's going to be really hard to align
our human effort if we can't come to
terms
with what we want out of humanity as a
as a collective conscious
species and the differences in
perception
it brings diversity and that's very good
and i find this to be
a really difficult contradiction
because diversity is unequivocally good
and all actual empirical research
diversity brings way more good than it
brings bad
but having a homogeny of ideas makes
order much easier
so i guess it's like what do we do
yes i'm very this is very hard to answer
i'm really stumbling through this so i
apologize
no i mean i i set you up for an
impossible spike i guess
i'm trying to think of how how we can
unwind it with examples i guess i was
thinking
um something that popped into mind was
the
the movie tarzan actually tarzan grew up
raised by raised by gorillas raised by
monkeys um when he comes
into reality with like proper
people they're drinking tea they have
etiquette these sort of things
they're flabbergasted by his actions
they're like wow what you're eating with
your hands you're such a
barbarian whatever um
these tarzan doesn't know that what he's
doing is wrong
okay he does it because it's not
inherently wrong it's just
when he exists within their proper
culture
it's it's improper it's not
but what we but what we do here this
might be leading something
what we do is we say bad other you say
that's bad or good
so um tarzan doesn't do the things that
we do
so he's bad he can't participate in what
we have going on here
um i don't know how to really relate
that to
i think that i think that we've hit a a
strange
almost dead end of what we're trying to
explain
so how do we how do we in continuing the
conversation how do we unwind
where we're at and go back to what's
important
sense making
explaining bias i really so
just with the sense making question in
general
just hard to see so much division even
though
i cleanly fit on one side of it just in
general i came to you know this is a
little bit of a vivid but
on the way driving here i kind of
realized that
the way that i look at politics
sometimes i think
that i've got my in group and we have a
definitive goal
the goal is to bring the most human
ubiquity
and
stop the stop suffering and exploitation
that's the goal
you know we want to dissolve power
structures so people are not
living in any kind of tyranny and just
genuinely as a collective
support each other like stop the
individualism
we have come to terms with the fact that
we need each other
to live innately and we don't need to
engage in all these systems that are
archaic and exploitative
and then there's another group of people
that are hyper individualistic and they
think that this
um this system is really good that it's
the ultimate proving ground
and i've always kind of disregarded
them as like like another you know
like it's easy to dehumanize these
people because you feel like they're
going against your thesis you know
like if this is what i believe and i
believe that you know like this is what
i want for humanity and this person
believes the opposite
you do the math and you say this person
doesn't want this for humanity which may
be true i don't know i don't know their
thesis or if they've come to one
even on their own but it's really easy
to dehumanize people like that and so
as i was thinking i'm like no matt even
if i get what i want these people still
need to be served by society
you know they're still they're not going
to go off on some ship you know
we need them right to be involved in
this but how do we get to the ubiquity
of wanting the same end goal hmm
that's true yes because it's not like
how do we prove to them that what we
want is more important than what
they want it's how do we continue this
human experiment
and continue coexisting i guess yeah how
do we accommodate everyone and i really
think it comes down to
being able to maybe not even agree on
the facts
or agree on the end goal but be able to
actually discuss it outside of this
performative
like battle of tribes
okay right reinforcement that we see on
the internet because
you see all these all like all with the
twitter wars
whatever whatever you get on any social
media you see any arguing
it's people are not arguing to stomp
this other person
well they are but they're arguing to
stop this other person in front of
people they already agree with
because hey look i owned xyz you know
yeah it's um it's a reinforcement it's
not um
it's not going forward i know it's so
cheesy because it's like no loaf no
right before
but really like as much as i don't like
it or do like it
people that starkly disagree with me
also participate in society and i really
care about their well-being i genuinely
do
i just think that their ideas aren't
going to bring them that and my ideas
will
i don't know if that's everyone's thesis
i don't know if people actually care
about others
some people but and i don't know how
they came to that
that is programmed as well but
how do we accommodate all of this and
realize what the real problems are
so that is the ultimate sense to be made
is
uh we're all in this together as a
massive collective
and how do we come together to deal with
it so what so what is we can point out
what is unhelpful to this
and some things that are unhelpful i
think of you know terms like um
so and so owns blah blah or libtards or
uh um like
name calling so so basic conversation
basic problem solving
um you see this in uh we all know
probably
a someone who's in a relationship who
they're they're on and off again
and they're always arguing and they get
to these mean ends of arguments
sometimes i
i mean not not everybody does this but
sometimes we'll see people who are
couples and they love each other very
much and we know they love each other
but they get to these edges of
conversation where they're both so
angry in there and they're just so
they just start attacking each other
it's yeah it's kind of like this like
you
your mom's fat or like okay big nose
okay like
we start attacking each other on these
really low level really low
consciousness
like weird attacks and that's where
we're meeting each other at to discuss
important conversations i think
i mean i don't want to get just stuck in
politics but we look at the
the recent um debate
we're forgetting what a debate's for
we're we're
we're trying to like we end up they end
up just insulting each other the whole
time joe biden and trump they end up
just
attacking um here's what you did wrong
here's what you did wrong here's
um that at one point trump like attacked
biden's son or something like that
and then vice versa it just it gets to
the point where as i'm watching
it i'm like how is any of this way of
conversation
helpful to what we're trying to do here
as humanity what is the point of this
what is the point of the debate so we
choose the best leader what's the point
of a leader
so we have someone who uh gives us all
a better life a good life and you know
uh
lowers the chance of suffering for
people in our in this society
um and you keep climbing up and it's
kind of just like
we all want love right um
we are digressing our conversations
because of this like slam culture um
that social media seems to be
clickbait viral slam culture yeah and
it's so okay so so what's happening
social media and
our today's media the technology is
it's really fueling a
shitty way of discussing it's really
fueling a
a mean way of talking about other people
who are different than you
and it's incredibly unhelpful it's
childish it's immature
it's um it's
it's it's throwing dirt on what we're
trying to do here which is
prosper not have suffering not like none
of w
we we don't meet on the places we agree
we find
weird places where we can insult each
other and and it's coming to this
schoolyard
bullying version of news media headlines
and stuff like that
um yeah i i
as much as i say i want cohesion i do
think actual disagreement and criticism
is super important for actually coming
to a end goal that is good
like this debate and these you shouldn't
attack people
ad hominem is like a fallacy like it's
unacceptable debate
but if you if they have an idea that has
blatant problems and you have an idea
that's going to fulfill the same goal
but do better
that's good you should say that we need
to actually have
smart people need to actually be having
debates right definitely
and we can being divisive is
fine as long as we're still coming to
like it's like i guess we just need the
same end goal
you know and it's how do you convince a
bunch of people what the same end goal
is going to be you know what do we want
out of society and i think it's
it's hard because nobody even asked that
like why do we have a government
why do we have any of these things it's
huge yeah why why nobody asked that why
do we have a government yeah
what is the role of the government why
do we order society in this way and how
do we deconstruct it
to maybe come to a ubiquitous angle
where we all do the best instead of
and you know you you know i'm
getting what i want because not even
because i necessarily want it but it's
because of what you don't want
you know like it's this own the lib own
own the alt-right
kind of thing where it's like i'm only
taking the stance
because it's gonna piss you off it's not
because i actually have an end goal with
it
and we get trapped in this uh i actually
hate the culture war because it takes
away
from the big systemic issues like uh
inequality just in general
racial monetary like these things that
create human suffering
just having a pissing match with each
other really takes away from dealing
with that and
you can even take a step further to
existential problems we spend all day
with our dick in our hands yelling at
somebody else that's honestly
really similar to us and we're never
going to get there and we're never going
to ask our leaders to get there because
they're using the media to make us fight
against each other
yeah and i mean the the social dilemma
on netflix is a good example of kind of
the
the wrong things that are being fueled
like the
uh all right our addictions to being
um uh what's the word
affirmed to our addictions to
validation um are
are leading us farther down it's like oh
okay that gets the clicks feed them more
of it
that gets them on on the on the platform
longer feed them more of it
the our our systems are being hijacked
in this way so
first step is knowing we have to have a
large swath of the population realize
this and i was talking about this with
my stepfather
you know you have this pendulum right
you get social media comes in
it swings and swings and swings and it
disrupts society a lot
i mean we can either realize at some
point in time that this is
so destructive for the fabric of reality
and our collective conscious and what
we're trying to do as a society even if
we haven't decided on that
there are some general themes we want
people to just do well
you know everybody wants to feel good
everybody wants to be secure
we either you know it swings back and we
realize hey
this isn't it and this goes out of
fashion until they realize that they
need to monetize it differently because
it really is the money that is the issue
i find money
to be a massive issue in most of these
problems government
social media it's the way it's monetized
or this ball
falls off this handle and we dive deeper
into it and no sense is made and we
self-destruct
because at this point it's either
self-termination or elimination of the
way social media is
there's no in-between we you cannot we
cannot carry on
making sense in the way that we're
currently doing or the lack thereof
it's just i i think that that
documentary was
terrifying and it was also enlightening
and i'm glad that it caught so much
traction
right from everyone like anyone that i
knew that saw it like my stepdad stopped
using social media
yeah i think it actually had had a
compounding effect yeah it's important
it's important that we have dissenting
opinions that are not politically
charged that just completely ridicule
the way things are
because you still well i mean
everything's innately political but
every single levy against structured
society is
really heavily politically charged which
is really hard to get around but
things like that are not it's like hey
we're all suffering from this
like this has to change or we're never
going to make sense of anything yes
what we used to have is never coming
back but we can find a way to go forward
better than this
because un indefinitely we must live
together yeah you can't just eliminate
people that don't agree with you
yeah it's not about the left winning or
the right winning it's about
we have a place where people of
differing opinions
all exist how do we make that work
i think we get caught up with my side
versus your side but it's like no
dude both sides must coexist or none of
us exist
yeah and it's easy to get into the weeds
though because if you're like you know
if this is my thesis and this side
doesn't want this
that's bad you know i think that my
ideas are going to bring the most human
happiness and joy and
and there's somebody that disagrees with
me holy so it's so hard to not get
trapped into it
well so so can we say that what's more
helpful for the prosperity of humanity
is people thinking about
people not just thinking about
themselves but thinking about
all of us yeah i'm not an individual
that's really okay i
i feel like a paradox because i
had one hand feel pretty deterministic
and i didn't get to choose nature and
nurture in my life and i was
born and everything that happened to me
was a cause and effect of that and
how much agency do you really have over
the real world but i also feel
like i'm the only thing in my life that
i can control
and i must master myself to affect
reality and have
my agency over the world in a way that's
positive but
on the other hand politically i'm a
collectivist if my neighbor does better
i do better
you know if civilization does good i do
good like the rising tide lifts all
boats like
it's getting away from the the
competition
of the way we structure things to come
to a cooperation
like we all labor for a reason it's
because we need things
as a society it's not just to make money
because we're just generating wealth
we're not laboring to help everyone like
how it's always been
we've stepped away from the agricultural
like once feudalism started we stepped
away from this you know you have a farm
and you feed the community and we come
together we work on this and it's a
there's a great sense of um
pride in it and once we got to a
like a capitalistic economy you now are
in direct competition to make somebody a
lot of money
that you don't you don't really care
about you're so disconnected from this
so if we can reorganize labor
and the way we structure all this to
where if your neighbor does good you do
good and everyone believes that
and these people in vietnam are just as
important as your neighbor we can
actually come together
and have more ubiquity but it's getting
people there with all the propaganda
machines
getting people to realize that this is
the goal of civilization right
is for us to prosper so how do we
how do we encourage people to think as
individuals how do we encourage people
to
question everything that they're
listening to question everything they're
reading
question the people even closest to them
with what they're saying
question their parents question
what's the incentive for people to
ask huh do i really believe this
before going out to the streets about it
and going and buckling down on our
identities
is it becoming familiar with um
i mean i i think that mindfulness has
helped me an incredible amount
with with this area kind of just
observing my thoughts and like what am i
thinking and then
i'm able to question them separate
myself from my thoughts
and then see like wait where does that
come up is that an influence that
of a video that i watched earlier is
that influence of something that i read
am i reacting because my identity feels
threatened
how can i separate my um ego identity in
the culture from what i actually believe
in
and also apply to it this filter of also
is this helpful is this
is this going towards the same direction
that we should be all going towards
which is
humanity continuing yeah
i think that just being super aware is
really important but it's
really hard i mean in the west we're
super tied to identity in general like
our culture is just
very very centered around a strong sense
of self which makes it way harder to
combat this because you see like
eastern countries don't really have a
problem with this honestly
not like we do i mean they have division
and they have authoritarians and
like bad governments but they don't have
this
fierce internal turmoil and i think
just being able to remove yourself from
ideas
because they're not you and analyze them
and just to to ruthlessly seek truth
regardless if you like the answer right
because ultimately if you come to a
realization or there is a study
like a real empirical data that proves
you wrong
that doesn't change the fact that it's
true i mean yeah
the media literacy is a big problem too
just being able to like actually
analyze media which just takes education
so you're gonna have to like work on it
but trying to construct a reality
outside of your twitter feed
um realizing that this this this thing
that you are not look that you're
looking at is not reality
right it's definitely not it's even less
reality than what you see in your daily
life
you know this is like a curated
constructed click bait
scrolly blue app you know that is just
made to hold you there and it's going to
confirm all your biases
and taking a step back and realizing
that is
definitely the first step but
it means self it's so cliche but just
self mastery
being you must be the mat you're
self-sovereign
you've got to be the master yourself or
you're going to fall for all of these
things i think a huge thing to point out
and that
is
self-mastery and self-actualization and
just trying to become
a better person whatever that might mean
to you as an individual i think
a lot of what we need to understand as
individuals
is you can change you aren't
just the way that you are we always try
to define ourselves well this is the way
that i am and this is exactly what i
think it's like well
is the way that you think helpful is it
harming you is it harming other people
this is what my dad thought so i think
this yeah and that is the death of
i mean once curiosity dies that is the
death of growth
yeah absolutely so we need to bring back
that child-like mindset of
you you know we all have like nephews
and stuff or we have just
the younger people in our life who we've
seen they just ask why what's that
why what's that we need to go back to
that i think as adults because
we're faced with this crazy amount of
data with
with the social media era the internet
era
the whatever the hell media is now is
we need to upgrade our our sense making
abilities
so we can actually make sense of what
we're taking in because we're just
taking it in and then fighting people
who don't take in the same stuff as us
yes you got to find out a why too for
yourself
like why do you believe the things you
do and what is the end goal of
your life and everyone's life
collectively
so so what's the goal of humanity like
massive questions like what's the goal
of humanity like what is the agency i'm
gonna
enthrust upon the world to make it
better right you know it's so easy to
get in the mindset of just
generate money just didn't you forget
like i'm
i have human excellency somewhere inside
of me that is
definitely more than just this rat race
money monster
like i could be here to do something
better than someone else could you know
like i am a i'm uniquely special
and there's something there's a niche in
the world that i can fulfill
if i get actualized enough to really
make a difference
and getting away i mean it's i know it's
way harder than it sounds
but i guess it just comes down to
self-actualization
set your goals and ask why a lot yes
you got to question all these structures
you got to set your goals for the agency
that you're going to push over the world
and i don't know man
i i think something that we can that we
can end on here
is something that helped me was
learning about like what are ethics and
what are my
ethics what are values and what are my
values what are my values
and how did i learn them have i ever
really thought about them what could be
my values that would be helpful to me
going forward
philosophy hugely like changed changes
my perspective
um it it makes me
i it points really within a lot which is
sometimes painful
which is sometimes uh makes you see
parts in yourself that you don't like
makes you
see things in the past that you've done
or said that you don't like but i think
that
when you're able to stand up say okay
i'm
willing and choosing to change my
beliefs about those things now
i'm willing and choosing to hear going
forward i'm going
to do these things and i think that
learning about ethics
morals values a lot of things that i say
throw the baby out the bathwater when a
lot of people just don't really believe
in religion
now a lot of people our age there's a
lot in
religion that was only kind of taught in
that area that like school doesn't
really touch
and i think if you're not in school any
longer
i invite you to study
these things values ethics morals
philosophy
they teach you about yourself in ways
that you didn't know existed
um and and you you study philosophy
heavily too so answer do you have
anything to add to that to anybody who
maybe they're maybe we sparked something
in them maybe they're like i don't know
i've never really questioned my beliefs
that much
where could they go how can we begin to
change the way that we think
the socrates said that the ends the
uninspired life is like not living at
all
or something synonymous with that and
until
i know i always every time i come on a
hammer that people should engage in
philosophy and i guess i don't give a
lot of actionable
tips on doing so but it's
there is wisdom like the way to live a
good life
and the way to analyze reality and
just concepts in general has been
thought about since people started
writing
and there is it's just already out there
all you have to do is engage in it
and i would highly recommend it has
changed me forever you become more
worldly
more ethical you care more about people
and you understand the nuance of
just a lot more things in context to
ancient wisdom
and modern science if you can engage in
these abstract thoughts and it's
definitely is difficult
but it is been the most helpful thing
for curating a worldview
that is um helpful and guiding me
through
what i need to do with my life more than
anything and i think when you can come
to terms with that sense making is
all easier because we have a goal
there's a there's actionable steps
you have a goal in mind you understand
reality better than you did before
because you're now questioning it and
you've seen other perspectives
and it doesn't it inspires divergent
thinking as well
because you're engaging in all these all
the greatest thinkers who have ever
lived
who say different things but they all
have excellent points and being able to
just have this amalgamation
of all these ideas and kind of figure
out what's going to work for you and
what you think reality is
to be really important yeah just just
for
all of humanity and i really
hammer home education like you just got
to continue to learn about stuff
because when you stop learning about
stuff you become
the unchangeable old man who has all the
opinions of the past
you know you must be fluid just like the
times you know
there's been more change in the last 50
years or since the industrial revolution
than there ever has in human history
and if you can't remain flexible as the
times are
you are most destined to have a
worldview that is
not excellent unhelpful yes yeah i
completely agree
um i i i think that's a good place to
end it i think uh
so what we'll try to maybe assess
a summary um on an individual level
not not amidst the podcast but i think
that we've um exhausted
our our minds by trying to figure out
what we're even trying to figure out
here
i think that we did well i think that we
um
did what we could and i like i said i
think this is going to be a multiple
part kind of series
on the junkyard love podcast because i
believe that it's important
i believe that
there really is a sense-making crisis
there's a sense making emergency
and we all have a personal
responsibility and i don't know i mean i
a lot of people listen to the podcast
are um our age a little bit older
um and i think that a lot of us see
what's going on
and we are kind of like what the what
the is happening here
and upgrading our sense making and
understanding why it is that we think
what it is that we think
is going to be able to help us gain more
intelligence
more knowledge and then in turn the
people in our families the people who we
work with
the people who we interact with the ways
in which we interact with each other
we can ripple effect this out
so um so i'm gonna just drop a couple
philosophers that uh
might be interesting to people right so
there's a stoic philosopher named seneca
i really like him he was a former slave
in greece or rome i can't remember him
but he
is his best student wrote all the stuff
down but that's really
uh helpful for self mastery just
stoicism in general i mean there are
flaws to every ideology and you must
realize that when you engage in
philosophy but it has
helped me quite a bit for analyzing
power structures
and just tyranny itself there is a
modern philosopher
probably the last 80 years her name is
hannah arendt she wrote a book on
tyranny it's just um
it's very prolific and good uh frederick
nietzsche
wrote on a lot a lot of topics human
suffering um
what is reality like just big concepts
he was generally like a renaissance man
of philosophy
i don't actually condone or agree with
all the things that all these people
have said but they are very good
perspectives for different time periods
different eras and different parts of
your life
and i recommend checking them out yeah
definitely and then a good way to check
them out like don't think like okay do i
need to enroll
in a class do i need to go to the
library and get these books like do any
of those things if you'd like
but nowadays we have youtube youtube to
me is i'm always pointing people
i know it's overly obvious i know it
seems like this like silly little thing
because that's where you watch
uh like ryan unbox his favorite toys and
your kids watch
the shark shark doo doo whatever baby
shark
like youtube is full of information and
it really is something that like
do not underestimate youtube there's so
many different schools of thought on
youtube and there's a lot to learn and
you don't have to actively sit there
with a pen and paper just put it on and
learn something new and expand your
knowledge
there's plenty of places philosophize
this after
school um uh the stoa
uh i don't know there's just tons of
places on youtube
being curious was free being curious
it's free so is youtube so that goes
pretty well
you just gotta engage in it yeah so so
check out some things literally type in
go to youtube and type in philosophy and
if you like the video
subscribe to them look at their other
videos just follow your bliss
and upgrade your sense making um
listener take care of yourselves as
always
love yourself please stretch please
drink some water
um spencer it's been great i i love and
appreciate your friendship man thank you
for embarking on this
very difficult very strange corner of
conversation that we're attempting
to have here and i hope we somehow get a
little further on it in the next part
and do our best jake thanks for having
me yeah yeah peace out
that's so difficult
you